Guide to the Judith M. Layzer Papers WAG.069
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Judith M. Layzer Papers
1969-2007
1970-1996
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Layzer, Judith M.
Layzer, Varese
WAG.069
2 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons
Judith Mushabac Layzer became an activist for women employed in New York City government and particularly for those in non-traditional blue-collar jobs when she worked as a contract compliance officer for the City during the John Lindsay administration. The collection consists of a small selection of records of Women in City Government United (WCGU) and a larger group of records of the Committee for Women in Non-traditional Jobs (CWNJ); Layzer played a leading role in both groups. The two organizations addressed a broad range of issues of importance to working women, including occupational choice, discrimination, availability of job training and health insurance problems. The collection includes attendance records, brochures, correspondence, flyers, fundraising plans, interviews, minutes, newsletters, clippings, press releases, photographs, reports, and surveys.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Judith Layzer, 1989. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1989.003 and 1989.001x.
A small amount of biographical information was added to the collection by Layzer in 2007. Another small addition was donated in 2010 by Judith Layzer's daughter, Varese Layzer. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2010.083, 2011.039, 2011.040, 2011.146.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Judith Mushabac Layzer received a B.A. degree from the School of Industrial and Labor Relations at Cornell University in 1962 and an M.A. from the City University of New York in 1967. She became a contract compliance officer, specializing in affirmative action provisions, in New York City's Bureau of Labor Services. Eventually she served as head of the Bureau's non-construction contract compliance unit. She was a leading member of Women in City Government United (WCGU, founded in 1969) and later was the founder and president of the Committee for Women in Non-traditional Jobs (CWNJ; originally founded in 1977, as the Committee for Women in Non-Traditional Trades). Women in City Government United consisted of employees of New York City government, primarily from the Mayor's Office, during the John V. Lindsay administration. Through petitions and meetings with mayoral officials, WCGU pressed for more appointments of women to high-level positions and improved health, pension and maternity benefits for all women employees.
Layzer recognized that there were already many women's groups in New York City, but she was interested in creating one that would concentrate on increasing women's participation in the nontraditional workplace. The Committee for Women in Nontraditional Jobs was composed of officials, primarily but not exclusively women, from a broad spectrum of organizations, private and public. The typical government employee participant held a responsible position within her/his own agency and could influence decisions on policy matters. The Committee also had a board of directors comprised of knowledgeable feminists from different sectors, including the law, trade-union leadership and academia. Through forums, conferences, radio interviews, video cablecasts and reports, the Committee brought to light and challenged employer practices unfair to women who wanted to pursue nontraditional employment but were discouraged by standard training, eligibility and hiring policies.
In addition to working with representatives of many industries to encourage the hiring of women, CWNJ focused on New York City Training and Assistance (TAP) programs. In 1979, CWNJ sought to change its status from a loosely organized volunteer organization to a more highly structured one that would include paid staff members. This attempt was only partially successful. The Women's Bureau of the U.S. Department of Labor offered the Committee a $20,000 development grant, but this offer was rescinded with the inauguration of President Ronald Reagan in 1980. That same year, CWNJ became the first independent women's organization appointed to the Employment and Training Planning Council, the advisory body responsible for planning the allocation of funds under the Comprehensive Employment and Training Act (CETA) Program.
Through its contacts with Percy Sutton and other public figures involved in media initiatives, the Committee became especially interested in opening up opportunities for women in the new and expanding field of cable television in the 1980s. Channel L, a local municipal cable station, provided the Committee with support for a one-hour video about the cable industry that was widely broadcast on cable. In 1983, the CWNJ received a Susan B. Anthony award from the New York City chapter of the National Organization of Women (NOW) in recognition of its work over the previous seven years, especially in relation to the cable television industry.
Under intense pressure from her superiors because of her uncompromising feminist activism, Judith Layzer was eventually reassigned to research tasks in her department and removed from direct involvement in compliance/enforcement work. She was eventually transferred to the Department of Transportation, where she was unsatisfied with her original assignment and went on to create a Quality Management Program, through which she offered group sessions on effective labor relations techniques to supervisors. She retired in 1996. In recent years Layzer continued her work as a political activist. She served on the Executive Committee of the Park River Independent Democrats. Additionally, as a long-term cancer survivor, she became especially active in the field of patients' rights, and initiated a legal case against Medicare on the issue of exclusion of certain medications from coverage. The case (Judith M. Layzer and Ray J. Fischer v. Hon. Michael O. Levitt, Secretary U. S. Department of Health and Human Services; case number SDNY 07CIV.11339[HB]) was decided in favor of the plaintiffs in March 2011.
Judith Layzer died in New York City in January 2010.
Scope and Content Note
The Judith Layzer Papers are comprised of Layzer's files of records of two feminist groups in which she played a leading role: Women in City Government United (WCGU) and the Committee for Women in Non-Traditional Jobs (CWNJ) (the latter was called the Committee for Women in Non-Traditional Trades [CWNT] from its inception in 1977 until mid-1979). The collection demonstrates the importance of government workers in advocating for, as well as providing services to, a sector of the workforce that had been widely discriminated against or ignored in both public and private employment. These files also document the pressure and obstacles that public employee activists faced when attempting to improve the system from within. Included in the collection are some case studies of non-traditional employment or training programs for women outside of the NYC area.
Files concerning Women in City Government United document issues pertaining to women's participation at the higher levels of City government and the genesis and implementation of Executive Order #71 (1969) on discrimination in employment. These materials include newspaper coverage of the group's activity, membership information, correspondence with Mayor Lindsay, documents related to health insurance and a report regarding the status of women in city government. The bulk of materials concerning the Committee for Women in Non-Traditional Jobs consists of meeting-related materials (minutes, attendance sheets, notes, and memos), correspondence, and materials on the cable industry and CETA. These materials include correspondence and other records from the early years of the Committee (1977-1979), when it was called the Committee for Women in Non-traditional Trades.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically within each series.
Organized into 2 series:
Series I: Women in City Government United Files, 1969-1975
Series II: Committee for Women in Non-Traditional Jobs Files, 1977-2007
Arranged alphabetically within each series.
Organized into 2 series:
Missing Title
I, Women in City Government United Files
II, Committee for Women in Non-Traditional Jobs Files
Separated Material
Audiotapes and videotapes have been separated to the Non-Print and Oral History Departments of the Tamiment Library.
New York (N.Y.).; Clippings (information artifacts); Memorandums.; Women -- New York (State) -- New York -- Societies, etc.; Reports.; Fliers (printed matter); Press releases.; Sex discrimination in employment -- New York (State) -- New York.; Women's rights -- New York (State) -- New York.; Sex discrimination against women -- New York (State) -- New York.; Interviews.; Women in the civil service -- New York (State) -- New York.; Newsletters.; Minutes (administrative records); Women -- Employment -- New York (State) -- New York; Plaques (flat objects); Photographs.; Women government executives |z New York (State) |z New York.; Correspondence.; Brochures.; Feminism -- New York (State) -- New York.; Committee for Women in Nontraditional Jobs; Women in City Government United (New York, N.Y.); Layzer, Judith M.; Layzer, Varese
- Series I: Women in City Government United Files, 1969-1975
  - Clippings, Membership Material and Press Releases, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Collapse of WCGU as an Active Organization: Letter to Susan Rosenfeld, Jul 1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and Memos: Government, Jan 1970-Apr 1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Health Insurance (Abortion and Maternity Leave), 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lindsay, John V.: Correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Status of Women in City Government" (Report, Study and Survey), 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Committee for Women in Non-Traditional Jobs Files, 1977-2007
  - Attendance Sheets (including CWNT), Jul 1977-Nov 1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cable Television: "Cable System Employment 1980-1981: A Report on the Status of Women and Minorities", Nov-82 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cable Television: Channel L, Oct 1981-Feb 1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Cable Television: Correspondence, Dec 1980-Dec 1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Cable Television: Equal Opportunity Clause, Mar 1981-May 1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cable Television: Forum Meeting (November 17, 1981), Oct 1981-Nov 1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Cable Television: Industry Reports, Clippings and Articles, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Cable Television: Meeting Notes and Announcements to CWNJ Taskforce, Nov 1980-Dec 1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Cable Television: Panel on Employment Opportunities for Women, Jun 1980-Oct 1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Cable Television: Programs Outside of NYC, Mar 1980-Jul 1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "California Study on Women in Nontraditional Employment," by Advocates for Women, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, Mar 1977-Nov 1977 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1978-Dec 1978 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1979-Jun 1979 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, May 1979-Nov 1979 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1980-May 1980 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, Jun 1980-Dec 1980 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1981-May 1981 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, Jun 1981-Dec 1981 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, Jun 1982-May 1982 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1982-Dec 1982 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1983-Oct 1983 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1984-Dec 1984 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1985-Dec 1985 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, Mar 1986-Jun 1986 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 31A)
  - "Crystal Ball in Your Past": CWNJ Video Project (with JL Interview), 1983 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Dissolution, 1993-1996 (Box 1, Folder 32A)
  - Embossing Stamp, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Equal Opportunity Clause and the Open Access Conference, May 1982-Jun 1982 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Exhibit: Movers and Shakers (Tamiment Library), 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 33A)
  - Financial (includes Correspondence), 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 33A)
  - Foundations and Fundraising Plans, Correspondence, and Mailing Lists, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Foundations and Fundraising Plans, Correspondence, and Mailing Lists, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Fundraising and Grant Articles: General, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Incorporation and Tax-Exempt Certificates, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Interview Transcript: JL with Miriam Ourin (on CWNJ History), with Related Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Layzer, Judith: Biographical and Patients' Rights Material, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Layzer, Judith: Interview, "The Cost of Healthcare" (CBS Evening News), 2007 (Box 1, Folder 39A)
  - Layzer, Judith: Notebooks (2), Jun 1980-Jan 1983 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Layzer, Judith: Writings, Ethnic Survey of Hospital Employees: New Occupational Possibilities, Feb 1970 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Layzer, Judith: Writings, Fleet Manager Perceptions of Vehicle Maintenance at the New York City Department of Transportation, Dec 1993 (Box 2, Folder 1A)
  - Layzer, Judith: Writings, My Healthcare Crisis, Sep 2007 (Box 2, Folder 1B)
  - Layzer, Judith: Writings, Staff Attitudes Toward Communication, Oct 1996 (Box 2, Folder 1C)
  - Mailing Lists: Advisory Board, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Mailing Lists: Cable Industry Contacts, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 2A)
  - Mailing Lists: Committee Members, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Mailing Lists: General, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Meeting Handouts (includes CWNT), 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Minutes (CWNT), Apr 1977-Dec 1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Minutes (CWNT), Feb 1978-Dec 1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Minutes (CWNT), Feb 1979-Apr 1979 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, Sep 1979-Dec 1979 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, Jan 1980-Dec 1980 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Minutes, Jan 1981-Aug 1981 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Ms. Foundation Grant, Mar 1980-Oct 1980 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - National Federation of Cable Programmers Conference, May 1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - New York Chamber of Commerce Conference of 1979, Apr 1979 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - New York City Department of Transportation, 1993, Undated (Box 1, Folder 14A)
  - New York Employment and Training Planning Council (ETPC) and CETA: Correspondence and Reports, Jun 1979-Dec 1980 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - New York ETPC and CETA: Correspondence and Reports, Jul 1981-Aug 1981 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Nontraditional Training and Employment Meeting with New York Attorney General, May 1981 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Occupational Education and Discrimination, Nov 1979-Apr 1981 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Occupational Education and Discrimination, Dec 1982-Dec 1984 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Occupational Education and Discrimination, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Organizational Plan for 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Photographs (Miscellaneous), 1981, undated (Box 2, Folder 21A)
  - Plaque (Department of Transportation, NYC), 1987 (Box 2, Folder 21B)
  - Port Authority: Correspondence and Memos, Aug 1979-Aug 1981 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Private Industry Council: Recruitment Programs and Mailing Lists, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Projects for Women in Non-Traditional Trades, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Publicity, undated (Box 2, Folder 24A)
  - Report on Boston's Nontraditional Occupations Program for Women (U.S. Department of Labor), 1978 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Report on the Status of Women in Jobs in the Private Sector, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Sketches, undated (Box 2, Folder 26A)
  - Susan B. Anthony Award (NOW), Jan 1983-Feb 1983 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Sweatshops and the Garment Industry, Apr 1980-May 1980 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - "Training Women for Nontraditional Occupations: A Report to CWNJ" by Judith Maughan (NYU), 1981 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - "Will There Be Equal Opportunity in Cable TV?", Apr 1982 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - "Will There Be Equal Opportunity in Cable TV?": Catalyst Media Evaluation, Feb 1982-May 1982 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - "Will There Be Equal Opportunity in Cable TV?": Editing Notes, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Videos: "Women in Nontraditional Work", undated (Box Shared Tamiment 024)